Guide to the Watts-Jones Family Papers 1800-1905 (Bulk 1806-1850) MS 681
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Watts-Jones Family Papers
1800-1905 (bulk 1806-1850)
MS 681
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.1 Linear feet (3 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, legal papers, financial documents, and printed material from the Watts and Floyd-Jones families. The material documents the family lives and business matters of Charles Watts Sr., Charles Watts, Jr., Henry Floyd-Jones, and Sarah Floyd-Jones.
Provenance
Purchase June, 1944.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Historical Note
Charles Watts, Sr. (17??-1811) was a cabinet-maker and merchant of Charleston, South Carolina. He married Catherine Beard and had two children, Charles Watts, Jr. and Helen Watts (1792-1872). Charles Watts, Jr. began work as a merchant for J & L Gladstones Merchants (Liverpool) but later became an attorney. Around 1818, he started a business with Moses Isaacs to run a boat propelled by horses on the Hudson River from Christopher Street to Weehawken, NJ. By 1820, the business had failed, and he continued to practice law.
In 1816, Helen Watts married Henry Floyd-Jones (1792-1862), a merchant with the company Jones and Bailey and a Major General of the Queens County Militia, 1st Division Infantry of the New York State Militia. Henry Floyd-Jones was also a member of the New York Assembly from 1829-1830 and a member of the State Senate from 1836-1840. Helen Watts and Henry Floyd-Jones had seven children: Charles (1817-?), Sarah (1818-1900), Henry (1820-1849), Edward (1823-1902), DeLancey (1826-?), Helen Watts, (1827-1855), and Josephine Katherine (1832-1905).
Sources:
Smith, Harry J. Jr. The Romance of the Hoboken Ferry. New York: Prentice Hall, 1931.
Floyd-Jones, Thomas. Thomas Jones: Fort Neck, Queens County, Long Island, 1695 and His Descendants the Floyd-Jones Family, With Connections from the Year 1066. New York, 1906.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, legal papers, financial documents, family histories, and printed material from the Watts and Floyd-Jones families. Although some family matters are discussed, the material mainly documents the business matters of Charles Watts Sr., Charles Watts, Jr., and Henry Floyd-Jones. There are some personal letters to Charles Watts, Jr. and Sarah Floyd-Jones as well as legal documents regarding the estate of Charles Watts, Sr.
Some of the correspondence, legal material, and financial documents relate to Charles Watts Jr.'s efforts to run a ferry on the Hudson propelled by horses. Letters dated 1820 from Henry Floyd-Jones to Charles Watts, Jr. urge him to get out of the business and imply that he was in financial trouble. A 1811 letter describes a hurricane and tornado in Charleston and a 1822 letter to Henry Floyd-Jones describes a yellow fever outbreak in New York. One letter to Charles Watts, Sr. dated January 1807 remarks on appropriate punishments for men guilty of sodomy.
Arrangement
The Watts-Jones Family Papers have been divided into the following series:
Series I: Watts Family Papers, 1800-1831
Series II: Floyd-Jones Family Papers, 1816-1904
Series III: Non-Family Members, 1807-1905
Series IV: Printed Material, 1861-1876
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
A letterbook of Charles Watts, Jr. can be found under BV Watts, Charles. Other material relating to the Floyd-Jones family can be located in the Floyd-Jones Family Papers.
Bailey, James S.; Campbell, Alexander; Fisk, Moses, 1759-1843; Floyd-Jones family; Floyd-Jones, Helen Watts; Floyd-Jones, Henry; Floyd-Jones, Sarah; Jones and Bailey; New York (State). Militia; Watts family; Watts, Charles, d. ca. 1811; Watts, Charles, Jr.; Accounts; Cabinetmakers; Charleston (S.C.)--Commerce; Correspondence; Ephemera; Ferries--New York (State); Hurricanes--South Carolina--Charleston; Lawyers; Liverpool (England)--Commerce; Merchants; New York (N.Y.)--Commerce; Steam-engines--Drawings; Woodworking machinery--Drawings; Yellow fever--South Carolina--Charleston--1822
- Series I: Watts Family Papers, 1800-1831
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains the papers relating to the personal and business affairs of the members of the Watts family. Most of the series consists of documents relating to Charles Watts, Jr. and Charles Watts, Sr., although some correspondence from Helen Watts is included. It is not always clear which Charles Watts is represented.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1806-1831
    The letters are arranged chronologically and consist of incoming correspondence to Charles Watts, Sr. and Charles Watts, Jr. There are a few letters from Helen Watts to her father, Charles Watts, Sr. The letters reflect the business and personal affairs of both men. The correspondence details Charles Watt Sr.'s businesses in Charleston, New York, and Liverpool and Charles Watts Jr.'s time as a merchant and an attorney. The financial troubles of Charles Watts, Jr are well documented. Letters dating from 1820 from Henry Floyd-Jones discourage Charles Watts, Jr. from remaining in the business of running the horse ferry to New Jersey. One letter to Charles Watts dated January 27, 1807 contains remarks on appropriate punishments for men guilty of sodomy.
    - Watts Family Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1806-1809 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1813-1815 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1816-1819 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Watts Family Correspondence, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries II: Legal Documents, 1803-1820
    This subseries contains legal papers of the Watts family including deeds, indentures, estate papers, and the will of Charles Watts, Sr. It includes documentation of a lawsuit against Charles Watts, Jr. for a physical assault. The subseries also consists of legal papers regarding the running of the horse ferry to New Jersey and documents from cases with Charles Watts, Jr. serving as an attorney.
    - Family Legal Documents, 1803-1820 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Will of Charles Watts, Sr., 1803 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Legal Papers re Estate of Charles Watts, Sr., 1811-1816 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Legal Papers re Hudson River Ferry, 1814-1819 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Legal Papers with Charles Watts, Jr. Acting as Attorney, 1813-1819 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III: Financial Documents, 1800-1820
    This subseries contains accounts, bills, and receipts from both personal and business expenses.
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1800-1805 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1806-1810 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1811-1815 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1816-1820 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Financial Papers re Hudson River Ferry, 1819-1820 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Finacial Papers re Estate of Charles Watts, Sr., 1811-1816 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Financial Documents re Family Property, 1807-1814 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Prices Current, 1809-1811 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Helen Watts- House Expenses, 1808-1811 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series II: Floyd-Jones Family Papers, 1816-1904
  Most of the material in this series relates to the business dealings of Henry Floyd-Jones. Other family members represented in the series include Sarah, Edward, and Marie Floyd-Jones.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1818-1904
    The majority of the correspondence is letters to Henry Floyd-Jones regarding militia matters and the business of Jones and Bailey. An August 1822 letter to him mentions a yellow fever outbreak in New York City. Frequent correspondents with Henry Floyd-Jones include Thomas Delancey and Henry Nicole. The few letters to Sarah Floyd-Jones, daughter of Henry Floyd-Jones and Helen Watts, relate to family matters such as the deaths of relatives.
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, 1818-1831 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, 1833-1846 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence (Sarah Floyd-Jones), 1847-1855 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, 1868-1869 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, 1876-1901 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Floyd-Jones Family Correspondence, Letters of Introduction for Edward Floyd-Jones, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Subseries II: Legal Documents, 1817-1841
    This subseries contains family deeds and titles as well as the papers and certificates related to the Queens County Militia.
    - Floyd-Jones Family Legal Documents, 1817-1841 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Legal Papers re Henry F. Jones's position as Major General of Queens County Militia, 1826-1841 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Subseries III: Financial Documents, 1816-1846
    The financial subseries includes the accounts, bills, and receipts of Henry Floyd-Jones.
    - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1816-1846 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Subseries IV: Family Histories, undated
    This subseries consists of family genealogies and the history of a family candle.
    - Family Histories, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series III: Non-Family Members, 1807-1905
  This series contains documents in which a person is either unidentified or the person's relationship to the Watts or Floyd-Jones families is unclear. Individuals include Alexander Campbell, George W. Scudder, and George Wilkes.
  - Correspondence, 1807-1905 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1809-1837 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Legal Papers, 1813-1863 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate Papers, 1842, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Printed Material, 1861-1876
  This series contains printed items such as drawings, lists, an award, and a theater bill. None of the items include the names of Watts or Floyd-Jones family members.
  - Drawings of a Steam Engine and a Wood Splitting Machine, [1871] (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Theater Bill, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Award from Philadelphia Internation Exhibition, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Printed Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)